<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>By the Mayor. Orders set dovvne for Blackvvellhall</title>
            <author>City of London (England). Lord Mayor.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1595</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 13 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 4 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A06229</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 16716</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S107593</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99843292</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99843292</idno>
            <idno type="VID">8010</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A06229)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 8010)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1605:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>By the Mayor. Orders set dovvne for Blackvvellhall</title>
                  <author>City of London (England). Lord Mayor.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[3] leaves   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>J. Windet for J. Wolfe?,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1595]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint from STC.</note>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; leaf 3 torn.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Wool industry --  England --  London --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:8010:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>woodcut of arms</figDesc>
               </figure>By the Mayor. Orders ſet dovvne for Blackwellhall.<figure>
                  <figDesc>woodcut of arms</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>VHereas by Common Counſell holden in the Chamber of the Guildhall of the Cittie of London, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the right honorable the Lord Mayor of the ſame Cittie, and the right worſhipfull the Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men his brethren, and the Commons in the ſame Common Counſell aſſembled, on the Ninth day of this inſtant moneth of May. One Act was made and agreed vpon, the tenor whereof heereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter followeth in theſe wordes. Whereas diuers good lawes, ſtatutes, and ordinaunces, haue bene heretofore deuiſed, and made, for the true and perfect making of clothes, and other the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities heereafter mentioned, and for the viewing, and ſearching of the ſame: And yet by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that a great part of the clothes and commodities, brought to the Cittie of London to be ſold, haue not beene brought to the open market place, or places appoynted for that purpoſe. But haue beene bought, and ſolde, in ſecrete and priuate houſes, and places, by ſuch as haue tranſported and vented them, in forreine partes beyond the ſeas, or retayled them in their ſhoppes at home or otherwiſe at their pleaſure: The ſaid clothes and other commodities neither haue bene, or could be conueniently viewed and ſearched, according to the true meaning of the ſayd lawes, ſtatutes and ordinances, and thereby as experience hath ſet forth, much deceiptfull and euill cloth, and other commodities, haue not onely beene vttered, ſold, and tranſported, from this Cittie of London, to forreine partes out of this Realme, to the great diſcredite of the ſayd Cittie and whole Realme, and the commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties thereof, But alſo retayled and vttered within the ſame Cittie, to the great offence, loſſe, and preiudice of many her Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties louing ſubiectes, the wearers of the ſame. For remedy whereof. Be it enacted, ordayned, and eſtabliſhed, by the authority of this Common Counſell, in manner and forme hereafter following. That is to ſay, that all, and all manner of Clothes, Ke<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, Frizes, Rugges, Bayes, Cottons, and ſtockinges, and all other commodities made of wooll, or mixt with wooll, or of flax, towe, or hempe, or mixt with any of them, or of ſilke, crewell, or thredd, or mixte with them or any of them, and which are or ſhalbee made, wrought, wouen, or knitte, within her Maieſties dominions or any the partes thereof. And alſo all Dowlaſſe, Lockeram, and Linnen clothes, made or to bee made in Brittaine, in the partes beyond the Seas, which ſhall bee brought to this Cittie of London, or the Liberties of the ſame, or to any parte thereof, be it bought by former bargaine, or to be ſold at a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny time from and after the tenth day of Iune next, ſhalbe brought to the common market place, or places thereunto appoynted, in, at, or neere Blackewellhall, within the ſayd Cittie of London, and there in the ſame market place or places or ſome of them, put to ſale and abſolutely ſolde and not els where, within the ſayd Cittie of London or the Liberties thereof, vppon payne to looſe and forfeite, all and euery the Cloth, Clothes, Wares, Merchandizes and other the ſayd commodities that ſhall be ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, ſold or vttered, otherwiſe then in manner, and forme aforeſayd, or the value thereof, Except alwayes that all ſuch Hamp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire Kerſies as hereafter ſhalbe bought in the market of Southwarke in the county of Surrey, ſhall and may be brought from thence into the Cittie of London or liberties thereof, to the houſe of him or them that hath or ſhall ſo buy the ſame. So that ſuch duties be paide for the hallage thereof vnto the clearke of Blackwelhall, as if the ſame had beene brought to the ſaid mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket of Blackwelhall, and except alſo that all ſuch Cloth and Clothes, and other the commodities aforeſaid as ſhall at any time or times hereafter be bought vpon any former bargaines, to be made before they ſhalbe brought vnto the ſaide Cittie of London, and which ſhalbe afterwardes brought to the ſaid Common market place or places, or any of them, and there preſented, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtred, and the duties of market roome paide, and a note in writing receiued from the Clearke for the ſame duties which ſhall be deliuered to him or them that ſo bought the foreſaid Clothes and other comodities before they or any of them ſhalbe pitched or harbored in any other place or places, within the ſaid Cittie of London, or liberties thereof, and alſo except all ſuch Cloth and Clothes or other commodities aforeſaid, which ſhalbe carried to any known Merchants houſe, and there laid down without his knowledge, if ſuch Marchante, or any for him ſhall make it knowen to the Clearke of Blackwelhall within three daies nexte
<pb facs="tcp:8010:2" rendition="simple:additions"/> following, and then pay the duties due for the ſame, and cauſe the ſame to be regiſtred as aforeſaid. And for that all and eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry perſon and perſons may take knowledge of the lawfull market places in the ſaid Cittie of London, for ſelling and buying of all the Cloth, Clothes, Wares, and other comodities aboue ſpecified. It is hereby notified, declared, ordained and enacted by the authority aforeſaid, that Blackwelhall within the ſaid Cittie of London, and the roomes therein or neere thereunto adioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, now or hereafter to be vſed a common market place or places, for the ſaid Cloth, Clothes Wares and other comodities are and ſhalbe the ordayned aſſigned and appointed markett place or places for all forreiners to ſell euery of the ſaide ſeuerall Cloth, Clothes, Wares and comodities in manner as thereunto heretofore, and now they haue beene and are accuſtomablie v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and not elſe-where. And it is alſo enacted, ordayned, and declared, by the authority aforeſayde, that from the ſayde tenth day of Iune next, the lawfull times for ſelling and buyng in any of the ſayd Markets, or market place or places, ſhall bee and begin weekely on euery Thurſday at one of the clocke in the after noone, and continue vntill foure of the clocke of the ſame af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter noone, and on euery Friday at eight of the clocke in the fore-noone, and continue vntill eleuen of the clock in the ſame fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noone, and ſhall likewiſe begin in the afternoone of the ſame Friday, at one of the clocke, and continue vntill foure of the clocke of the ſame Friday in the after-noone, and ſhall begin againe euery Saterday, at eight of the clocke in the fore-noone, and ſhal continue vntill eleuen of the clocke in the fore-noone of the ſame day, and that the ſayd howers hereby appointed and limited for the beginning and ending of euery the ſayd market times ſhall be knowne by the ringing of the market bell in Blackwellhall aforeſayd appoynted for that vſe and purpoſe. This to be held and continued weekely euery weeke throughout the yeare, from yeare to yeare, (the twelue dayes in Chriſtmas onely excepted.) And that all and euery ſuch Cloth, Clothes, and other com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities before ſpecified as ſhalbe there put to ſale at any other time or times, then is afore limited ſhalbe forfeyted. And it is further ordayned and enacted that from and after the ſaid tenth day of Iune next no maner perſon or perſons not being free of the ſaid Citty ſhall by himſelfe or any other for him or by his meanes or practiſe bargaine or ſell in any place or places within the liberties of this City, out of the ſaid aſſigned market place or places any of the ſaid Clothes, Kerſies or other commodities, nor ſhall buy any of the ſame within any the ſaid aſſigned market place or places to the intente to ſell the ſame againe in any of the ſaide aſſigned Market places or elſwhere, within the ſaide Cittie or liberties thereof, vpon paine to forfeite and looſe for euery ſuch offence the Cloth, Clothes, Kerſies and other the ſaide commodities ſo bought or ſoulde, or the value thereof. And alſo that euery perſon and perſons being free of this Cittie, which ſhall harbour or receiue the ſaid Cloth Clothes or comodities ſo bought or ſoulde contrarie to the tenor of this Act and the true meaning thereof, ſhall forfeit and looſe his freedome, and not to be thereunto readmitted but by the Lord Maior, Aldermen and Common Councell of the ſaide Cittie for the time being. And it is likewiſe hereby further enacted and ordayned that no perſon or perſons now free or here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after to be made free of the ſaide Cittie, ſhall from and after the ſaide tenth day of Iune next ſell or cauſe to be ſolde, any Cloth, Clothes, Kerſies or any other the comodities aforenamed either in his owne name, or for or in the name of any other within the ſaide Common Markets or any of them, vpon paine to forfeit and looſe euery ſuch Cloth, Clothes and other comodities ſo ſolde or the value thereof. And to the intent to cut of the great fraude and abuſe vſed by ſundry perſons being free of this City, and others by forreine buying and ſelling, contrary to the auncient lawes, cuſtomes and liberties of the ſame Cittie, and for the better finding out of the ſame fraudulent dealings. It is further enacted by the authoritie aforeſaid that the Clearke or officer for the collecting of duties due for the harbouring and pitching of clothes at the ſaid Market of Blackwelhall and places aforeſaid ſhall keepe a Regiſter booke weekely throughout the whole yeare, of the names and ſurnames of the ſaide Clothmen and Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, owners of ſuch Clothes and Kerſies, and other comodities, as ſhalbe bought vpon any former bargaine, before they ſhall be brought to the ſayd Citty, and which ſhall be brought to the ſayd Market place or places, according to the tenor of this Act, and ſhall regiſter the true nomber, of ſuch Clothes, Kerſies, and other commodities, together with the names and ſurnames of the ſayd Free-men, or other buyers and ſellers of the ſame: Vppon payne that the ſayd Officer ſhall for not keeping the ſayde Booke truely and faythfully as aforeſayd, and for not giuing a note in writinge, for the dueties payde to him or them that ſhall pay the ſame, according to the true meaning of this Act, ſhall forfeit and looſe his ſaid office. And if the owner of the ſaid goods or his Carrier, be they forriners or free, ſhall deny to the ſaide Officer to giue the true names and ſurnames of the buyers and ſellers with the iuſt nomber, of all ſuch Clothes and Kerſies, and other commodities aforeſayd, ſo brought to the hall aforeſayd.
<pb facs="tcp:8010:3"/> Then it is hereby further ordeyned and enacted, that the ſaid buyers and ſellers whether they be free or forreyners ſhall haue no benefite of the exception aboue ſpecified in this preſent Act, concerning former bargaines, but ſhalbe bound to put to ſale the ſame Cloth, Clothes and comodities aforeſaid in Blackwelhall Market, or in other the place or places appoynted as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayd, ſayd, as though there had bene no former bargayne of the ſame Clothes or other commodities. And for the better reformation of the offences and abuſes, purpoſed to be reformed and amended, by this preſent Act of Common Councell, and the more ready execution of the ſame. It is finally enacted, ordayned, and eſtabliſhed, by the authority aforeſaid, that all, and all maner Cloth, Clothes, Wares, commodities, ſomme and ſommes of money, and other thinges whatſoeuer, that ſhall bee forfeyted by vertue of this Acte ſhall bee obtayned, leuied, or recouered, either by ſeizure, or els by Action of debt, bill, plainte, or information, in the name of the Chambe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>laine of the ſayd Citty <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>ing in the Queenes Maieſties Court holden in the Chamber of the Guildhall of the ſayd Citty, before the Mayor and Aldermen of the ſame, for the time beeing, wherein no Eſſoigne, protec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or wager of law ſhall bee admitted or allowed. And that all the paynes, penalties, and forfeytures, to bee had or recoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by vertue of this Acte, the charges of recouery deducted, ſhall bee deuided into three equall partes, whereof one third parte ſhall bee imployed to the Mayor and Comminalty of the ſame Citty, towards the mainetenance and reparations of Blackwell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hall aforeſayde: One other third parte to the vſe of the poore children of Chriſtes Hoſpitall within the ſayd citty, And the other third parte to him that will ſue for the ſame, beeing a Free-man.</p>
            <p>Now to the ende that all perſons whome the ſayd Acte may in any ſorte concerne, may take knowledge therof, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by way the rather avoyde the daunger of the penalties therein contayned, The Right honorable the Lord Mayor of the city aforeſayde, and the Right worſhipfull the Aldermen his brethren, Haue thought good by Proclamation to publiſh the ſame. Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted at the Guildhall of the cittie of London, the thirteenth day of May, in the ſeauen and thirtieth yeare of the Raigne of our Soueraigne Lady Elizabeth by the grace of God Queene of England, France, and Ireland, Defendor of the Faith &amp;c.</p>
            <closer>God ſaue the Queene</closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:8010:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8010:4"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
